[ III ]
NARRATOR : I busied myself to think of a story
which would speak to the mysterious fears of our nature
and awaken thrilling horror .
One to make the reader dread to look around .
To curdle the blood , and quicken the beatings of the heart .
[ III ]
[ GRUNTING ]
SAILOR 1 : Tell the captain , we 've got to take in the topsail .
She 's going to rip !
Please , captain ! We have to drop the sails !
All hands to the mast !
Take the wheel ! Come on !
SAILOR 1 : Captain , we 've hit the ice ! We 've hit the ice !
Iceberg ahead !
Hard to starboard !
SAILOR 2 : Go back !
[ SCREAMING ]
Help ! Help !
Help ! Hold on , Vernon !
Hold on !
WALTON : Put your backs into it , men !
Let 's go !
Captain , this is useless . The ice stretches for miles .
What do you suggest we do ? Lay down and die ?
The men are exhausted , sir . They can 't go on , man .
I tell you , I have not come this far to give up now .
They knew the risk when they signed on .
And we are gonna chop our way to the North Pole if we have to .
Then you run the risk of mutiny , captain .
Did you say mutiny ? Yes I did , sir .
We proceed north as planned .
At the cost of how many more lives ?
As many as it takes !
[ CREATURE HOWLS ]
[ BARKING ]
There 's something out there .
MAN : What is it ?
What the hell is that ?
Who is your captain ?
I am .
Who the devil are you ?
I 've no time to talk .
You bring your men and your weapons and follow me .
Now ! Stay where you are .
I give the orders here .
[ CREATURE HOWLS ]
Get the dogs ! Get them !
Leave them .
They 're already dead .
[ GROWLING THEN WHIMPERING ]
[ CREATURE ROARS ]
Get back to the ship now !
Everybody back to the ship !
[ III ]
Bears don 't kill like that , nothing does .
MAN : Maybe it wants the man with the captain .
Or it wants the captain .
It 's the devil come for the captain .
For the last time , I made my way from St. Petersburg to Archangel on foot .
From there I took a whaling ship north .
When we hit the ice , I used the dogs .
[ CREATURE HOWLS ]
What 's out there ?
[ CREATURE PANTING ]
Listen to me . I have spent six years planning this , my entire fortune .
I will not be stopped by you or some phantom .
Do you share my madness ?
What , then ? No. not madness .
There 's a passage to the North Pole , and I will find it .
At the cost of your own life ? The lives of your crew ?
Lives come and go .
If we succeed , our names will live on forever .
I will be hailed as the benefactor of our species .
You 're wrong .
L , of all men , know that .
Who are you ?
My name ...
is Victor ...
Frankenstein .
[ HARPSICHORD PLAYING ]
Mother !
Oh , my wonderful son Victor !
You are the handsomest , kindest , cleverest ,
most wonderfulest boy in the whole world !
[ WHOOPS THEN LAUGHS ]
MRS. MORITZ : Madam ! You will spoil the boy , really .
FATHER : Would you and your daughter leave us , please , Mrs. Moritz ?
Doctor .
Come along , Justine .
Victor , this is Elizabeth . She 's coming to live with us .
She 's lost both her mother and father to the scarlet fever , Victor .
She 's an orphan now .
You must think of her as your own sister .
You must look after her , and be kind to her .
Always .
[ III ]
Mother , oh . How is the imminent arrival ?
Oh , a little frisky today . Yes .
When you were a little boy , you used to chase fireflies in the field .
Yes , and when I trapped them in my jar , they died .
Yes . And do you remember how you cried ?
Yes . Because you wanted to keep them
glowing by your bedside
to light you as you read .
You were so hungry for knowledge . Such a serious little boy .
You 've become such an earnest young man .
All these strange and ancient books .
You 'll be an even greater doctor than your father .
But you know , Victor , life shouldn 't be all study .
There 's such fun to be had .
Oh .
Give me that back . No .
Give me that back , Mother .
[ HARPSICHORD PLAYING ]
[ LAUGHING ]
MRS. MORITZ : Change partners . And twirl !
Now , Caroline . You 're right .
You mustn 't exert yourself . Please . I know .
MRS. MORITZ : Don 't worry , madam . Your new baby will be a natural dancer .
Excellent .
You 'll be the envy of all the young ladies and gentlemen .
[ HARPSICHORD CLANKS ]
Justine .
Justine , may I have this dance ?
[ LAUGHS ]
[ GRUNTS ]
MRS. MORITZ : Madam ! Hurry !
[ GRUNTING ]
Sir . You must make a decision !
FATHER : How can I ? The baby 's in the wrong position .
I can 't proceed ... I can 't ...
[ MUTTERING INDISTINCTLY ]
Cut me . Save the baby .
[ CAROLINE SCREAMS ]
[ III ]
She 'll be all right .
Your father 's the finest doctor in Geneva .
[ FATHER SOBBING ]
Father ?
Father , how is she ?
I did everything I could ... Everything I could ...
VICTOR : Mother ? Mother !
Bring her back .
Please , bring her back .
No !
[ VICTOR SOBBING AND MURMURING INDISTINCTLY ]
Oh , Mother .
You should never have died . No one need ever die .
I will stop this .
I promise .
ELIZABETH : Victor , you 're completely obsessed . Please explain what that is .
VICTOR : It 's energy . It never disappears , it merely changes form .
It 's possible to convert this candle wax
into the convulsions of a mechanical dog .
But the applications of this are limitless . Really .
Oh , please come outside , Victor . It 's such a beautiful day .
Go away , I 'm busy .
What 's this ?
It 's for spraying down the electric eels .
[ LAUGHING ]
Now , put it down . Put it down . It 's not for playing with .
It 's not for playing with . Put it down , put it down- - Don 't do that .
I warned you . Don 't- - Don 't- - Give me that , you little ...
VICTOR : Come on !
[ ELIZABETH VICTOR SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
Yes ! Come on !
After all , we should be grateful to Victor
for abandoning his experiments for one afternoon .
Well , who says I have ?
What do you mean ?
[ THUNDER CRASHES ]
Look ! ELIZABETH : We 're all going to die .
You knew this was going to happen . No , not for certain .
But I had hoped the conditions would be right .
They 're quite common here at this time of year .
I 've never seen one quite as large as that , though . Look .
Isn 't it wonderful ? Victor , you shouldn 't have done this .
It 's all right , it 's all right .
We must take cover . A tree !
No , no , no . That 's exactly the wrong thing to do .
It 's potentially a much larger conductor than we are .
Victor , what about Willie ? Um ...
What are we to do ? Come on .
VICTOR : Now , everyone , spread out . Elizabeth , take this . Now , quickly .
Come on , quickly ! ELIZABETH : What is that ?
VICTOR : Dig it right into the ground . Go ahead .
ELIZABETH : Now what ? VICTOR : Justine , take this . Come on .
JUSTINE : Willie ! VICTOR : Everyone down .
[ LAUGHING ]
VICTOR : Give me your hands . It 'll be fine . Now take him . Now , that 's good .
ELIZABETH : Victor , I hope you know what you 're doing .
VICTOR : Willie ? Willie , don 't look up !
Willie . Victor- -
Wait ! One , two , three ...
[ III ]
Now .
[ ELECTRICITY CRACKLING ]
VICTOR : So how do you feel , Elizabeth ?
ELIZABETH : Alive .
[ CLASSICAL MUSIC PLAYING ]
[ LAUGHING ]
Ladies and gentlemen , dear friends . Gather round and listen .
As you probably know , tomorrow my dear son Victor
leaves me to pursue , what I 'm sure
will be an illustrious career in a profession
I , myself , am not altogether unassociated with .
Ha , ha . Oh , modesty .
[ LAUGHING ]
No . My - My- - My one regret is that his mother
my late wife , is not here
to share the pride
which our son fills me with tonight .
Yes .
She wanted you to have this , Victor .
On your graduation .
And in it she has written :
" This is the journal of Victor Frankenstein . "
The rest of the leaves are blank ,
to be filled with the deeds of a noble life .
[ GUESTS CLAPPING ]
[ CLASSICAL MUSIC PLAYING ]
We 'd , uh , better go in , before they miss us .
Just a little while longer . Please .
I don 't know when we 'll be alone together again .
[ LAUGHING ]
Oh , dear Victor .
I shall miss you laughing at me .
I 'll miss you making me laugh .
So ...
how do brothers and sisters say goodbye ?
Perhaps they never have to .
I won 't , if you won 't .
[ III ]
Are you my sister ?
Sister ...
friend ...
lover .
Wife ?
Yes .
Then come with me to Ingolstadt . Marry me now .
Victor , no . Well , then I 'll stay .
Oh .
I want more than anything else in the world to be your wife .
But as long as you 're away , I belong here .
I want to make this house live again .
I want to make this a great home for our children .
And now you must go , and do the great things you need to do .
I want you so much .
I 'll be here when you return .
Each holiday . Every visit .
Then on our wedding night .
Until our wedding night .
[ III ]
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
WOMAN : Lots of stairs , I 'm afraid .
How was your journey ?
It was very good , thank you . I made very good progress
over the mountains . Clear run . Good . I am pleased .
Well , as I said , we 've only got attic space .
VICTOR : It 's exactly what I 'm looking for .
But Frau Brach , there will be a great deal
of scientific equipment and rigging to be delivered .
Every day , I 'm afraid , for the next week . I trust you have no objections .
I 'm sure you appreciate the need for a proper laboratory , madam .
Oh , Putzi likes you .
[ III ]
This will be perfect .
MAN : " The foolish and vain force their views by the rod .
But knowledge is power only through God . "
Our motto . Easily forgotten by you young men in a hurry .
[ LAUGHING ]
But perhaps the greatest mistake that all students make
during their time here , is to suppose
that they can ever have an original or creative thought .
We have all imagined that in our time .
But gentlemen , you have not come here in order to think for yourselves .
You are here to learn how to think for your patients .
You must learn , therefore , in the first place
to submit yourselves
to the established laws of physical reality .
But surely , professor ,
you don 't intend we disregard more philosophical approaches ?
Philosophical ?
Those which stir the imagination as well as the intellect ,
as in Paracelsus , for example .
Ah , Paracelsus . An arrogant and foolish Swiss .
Albertus Magnus ?
His nonsense was exploded 500 years ago .
Cornelius Agrippa ?
A sorcerer . An occultist . What is your name ?
Victor Frankenstein , sir . Of Geneva .
[ STUDENTS CHUCKLE ]
Oh-ho . Another Swiss .
Mr. Frankenstein , here at the University of Ingolstadt , we teach- -
And indeed , hope to advance . - -the science of medicine .
Chemistry , biology , physics . We study hard science .
Yeah , but surely , professor , the greatest possible advances lie in combining these things .
We do not study the ravings of lunatics and alchemists
hundreds of years in their graves
because their kind of amateur , fanatical , fantastical speculation
does not heal bodies or save lives .
Only science can do that .
[ STUDENTS MURMUR AND APPLAUD ]
Now , have we your permission to continue ?
[ CHATTERING ]
Nice coat . Why , thank you .
Don 't take it too hard .
It 's just that Krempe doesn 't approve of public humiliation .
I am not mad !
My dear fellow , of course you 're not .
In fact , that 's just the sort of thing I 'd expect a perfectly rational person
to say to a complete stranger .
Henry Clerval , by the way , and I 'm completely crazy .
Victor Frankenstein . Of Geneva .
Of Geneva . Yes , I noti -
Why don 't you look where I 'm going ?
That 's Schiller . Ornement of the playmg field .
Really . He 's new as well .
You can tell because he goes around looking at things with his mouth open .
What are you here for ?
Research . Very grand .
I 'm here to become a mere doctor .
I 'm told it has something to do with healing the sick .
Which is a pity , really , because I find sick people rather revolting .
Still , I 'll have a good time , get my degree- -
If I can stop failing Anatomy .
- -And settle down to relieve rich old ladies of their imaginary ailments
and then relieve their very real and beautiful daughters .
Who was that ? He was at the lecture .
Ah . That 's Waldman .
Ah , that 's Waldman . Yes .
Interesting case . They say in his youth
he could break into heaven and lecture God on science .
Ran into trouble with the authorities a few years back .
Something to do with illegal experiments .
But what kind of experiments , I wonder ?
So what was it you were saying ? Uh ...
Rich old ladies and their daughters ?
Yes , it 's a life of sacrifice , I know , but someone 's got to do it .
[ BOTH CHUCKLE ]
[ HORSE NEIGHS ]
[ III ]
WALDMAN : And that is why the central nervous system
and its crowning achievement , the brain ,
are as complicated and mysterious a set of organs
as you are ever likely to encounter .
Mr. Frankenstein , the incision is yours .
Excellent .
Mr. Clerval , you may remove the cranial lid .
" Henry , now fully recovered , and continues his struggle to pass Anatomy . "
I was always terrible at anatomy .
" Professor Waldman is very tolerant of him , and of myself .
I 'm learning a great deal . "
Professor Waldman is remarkable . And so is Henry .
" God bless you , all my love , Victor . "
That 's very nice . " P.S. I 've fallen in love . "
I beg your pardon ?
" She 's dark , sleek , and beautiful ,
and always wags her tail whenever she sees me .
Her name is Putzi , and she 's the friendliest sheepdog that I 've ever known . "
[ LAUGHING ]
" P.S. Elizabeth , I dream of how your hair shines ... "
VICTOR : " Of how your lips taste . I dream of your arms and breasts
and of the time on our wedding night when we will be atone together at last . "
WILLIE : What else does it say ?
It says , " I 'm working very hard to make lots of new friends . "
More coffee , anyone ?
Once and for all , Frankenstein ! Life is life , death is death .
These things are real .
They are absolute . That is rubbish and you know it !
That premise has been repeatedly challenged by members on your own staff !
Yes , you , sir ! We don 't know where life ends or death begins .
Hair continues to grow after what we choose to call death . So do fingernails .
We know that a man 's brain may die
but his heart and lungs may continue to pump and breathe .
Now , you know that .
Mr. Frankenstein of Geneva , I warn you
what you are suggesting is not only illegal , it is immoral .
Rubbish !
" Dear diary , why does no one understand me ?
P.S. I am not mad . "
WALDMAN : You .
Explain yourself . Professor , I 'm sorry .
Listen , I came here to learn all about the new science .
About galvanism , Franklin 's experiments .
The combination of modern disciplines with ancient knowledge
in an attempt to protect and create- - To create what ?
Sir , we can change things . We can make things better . You know that .
We are on the verge of undreamed-of discoveries
if we only have the courage to ask the right questions . Now , you must help me . Please
Come on .
Victor ... VICTOR : Come on .
[ III ]
Henry -
Lock the door .
Now , for thousands of years
the Chinese have based their medical science on the belief
that the human body is a chemical engine run by energy streams .
VICTOR : That 's fascinating . Then how do they explain- - ?
Don 't touch that !
Their doctors treat patients
by inserting needles like these into the flesh
at various key points , to manipulate these electric streams .
I see .
So electricity is the key .
Now , look at this .
[ III ]
[ BOTH GASP ]
Go on , touch it .
It feels warm . It is .
Yes . How do you do ?
Aah ! Turn it off !
I can 't , it 's not working . Try to stay calm , Henry .
It 's simply a matter of reducing the polarity in your body 0r in the arm .
A monkey 's arm is basically the same as a human being .
No arm is this strong ! Now , this must work .
[ ELECTRICTY BUZZES ]
Let me help you , professor .
You shall , of course , tell no one .
They wouldn 't believe you anyway .
Dearest Victor . Nothing much changes here .
Mrs. Moritz continues to love and torment Justine , in equal measure .
Willie grows more precocious every day ,
and Father almost expires with pride
at the very thought of you and your work .
And I ...
Well , I just miss you , very much .
Please write soon , Victor .
VICTOR : ' No , I 'm serious . You take vaccine , for instance .
Thirty years ago the entire concept of vaccine was unheard of
and now we save lives every day .
But that isn 't the whole answer . What do you mean ?
That sooner or later the best way to cheat death will be to create life .
HEN RY : Now you 've gone too far .
There 's only one God , Victor . No , leave God out of this .
Listen , if you loved someone , they had a sick heart ,
wouldn 't you give them a healthy one ?
Impossible . VICTOR : No , ifs not impossible .
We can do it , we 're steps away .
And if we can do that- - If we can replace one part of a human being , we can replace every part .
And if we do that , we can design a life .
We can create a being that will not grow old or sicken .
One that will be stronger than us , better than us .
One that will be more intelligent than us , more civilized than us .
In our lifetime ? No .
[ III ]
How close did you get , professor ' ?
Too close .
Professor , I beg you , let me see these notes .
No . My work now , and its application ,
lies exclusively in the preservation of life .
I abandoned my other researches many years ago .
Why ?
Because they resulted in abomination .
[ WOMAN SCREAMING ]
[ PEOPLE SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
You 're not sticking that in me . It 's got a pox in it , I hear .
Pox ? They 've given us pox ? That 's right . Pox .
It 's not pox , it 's a vaccine that will prevent a plague in this city .
What 's that ? It 's a tiny , harmless amount
of anti-smallpox serum . You just said pox !
WALDMAN : I said it was harmless .
It 's a necessary precaution , without which this godforsaken city
would be immediately put under quarantine .
You doctors kill people . I don 't care what you say . You 're not sticking that in me .
Yes , I am . It 's the law !
Sit him down , someone . Come on .
You 're not sticking that in me !
[ GRUNTS ]
Sir ? Professor ? Sir ?
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY AND WOMEN SCREAMING ]
Find him !
Come on ! Come on ! Come on !
It 's no use , Victor , he 's gone .
No ! No , Henry ! Let him go !
No ! No , this shouldn 't happen ! Let him go ! Victor , stop !
VICTOR : It shouldn 't happen ! HEN RY : Stop ! Victor .
It need not happen !
[ CROWD JEERING ]
MAN : The hell with you !
Whatever you say , whatever you call it , you doctors are killers .
You murder people ! Evil ! You 're evil !
Evil !
You 're the ones that deserve to die . God will punish you . He 'll punish you !
God will punish you !
[ CHEERING ]
My God , you were so close ! Of course , the power !
The materials were wrong . You needed auxiliary sources .
" The experiment a failure .
Resulting reanimant malformed and hideous to behold .
This factor dependant on the appropriate raw materials . "
Raw materials ...
[ III ]
[ THUNDER RUMBLING ]
VICTOR : Come on , Henry . HEN RY : I can 't , Victor .
I can 't help you . You won 't help me .
What are you frightened of ? Everything ! What do you think ?
And what if the authorities- - ?
We 'll do this in secret . I 've got the raw materials , I 've got Waldman 's journals .
Together we know more than Krempe 's whole staff .
You stole Waldman 's journals ?
We owe it to him to complete this work .
He was one step away . He never wanted this .
Couldn 't face it , there 's a difference .
Even if it were possible , and even if you had the right- -
Which you don 't . - -to make this decision for us ,
can you imagine for one second that there wouldn 't be a terrible price to pay ?
I think for the chance to defeat death and disease ,
to let everyone on this Earth have the chance at life ,
sustained , healthy life ,
to allow people who love each other to be together forever ...
For all of that , I think it 's a risk worth taking .
[ III ]
ELIZABETH : Please , Justine , just leave me alone .
I won 't talk about it .
But all these letters , you read them to us yourself every week .
I wrote them . I wrote the letters .
He hasn 't written to me in months .
Elizabeth ...
Something horrific is happening to him . I can feel it .
At first I wasn 't sure , but I knew I had to hide it from Father .
Now there are rumors of cholera .
I can look after Father and Willie . You go to lngolstadt- -
No , that 's not possible . He won 't want me .
He 's probably found someone else .
If he was mine , I would have gone already .
But he isn 't mine .
He 's yours , and you must go to him .
Raw materials , that 's all they are .
Tissue to be re-used .
The very finest brain .
MAN : But they all died of cholera , sir . No matter .
Thank you .
The assembled organs must have the appropriate nutrients and heat
and crucially , more direct power .
More direct power .
[ SCREAMING ]
VICTOR : Amniotic fluid is the chief biogenic element .
The subject is injected with this . The copper acupuncture needles pierce the flesh
at all key energy points .
Now , after the removal of current , the dead toad should retain animation .
But independently of external power sources .
Yes .
That 's it .
That 's the combination . That 's the combination !
That 's it !
[ CROAKING ]
[ III ]
[ KNOCKING ON DOOR ]
HENRY : Victor ? Victor !
Victor , open the door !
Victor , please ! What do you want ?
There 's cholera . It 's an epidemic !
The city 's been placed under martial law .
Are you listening to me , Victor ? Yes . And ?
The militia 's arriving to quarantine the city .
Most of us are getting out while we still can .
Krempe knows that you 're here , for God 's sake . What if he tells the authorities ?
Goodbye , Henry .
ELIZABETH : Victor , it 's me .
Elizabeth .
Can you hear me ?
Victor , I have to see you .
Go away . ELIZABETH : Please , Victor !
I won 't leave here until you see me .
Come in the side door .
Alone !
What 's happened to you ?
How can you live here like this ?
And that stench .
Don 't go in there ! Aah !
We have to leave . It isn 't safe . No , I have to stay .
Even if it means you 'll die ? Yes .
[ III ]
Well , let me help you .
No , that 's impossible .
We made a promise .
Victor , I beg you .
Look , I know that this is difficult for you to understand
but I cannot abandon this work now .
It is too important . Not just for me , but , believe me , for everyone .
And it must come first .
Before us ?
Elizabeth ,
I love you so much , but ...
Goodbye .
[ III ]
[ CRYING ]
Elizabeth ! Elizabeth !
[ SOBBING ]
Oh , God ! Elizabeth !
Elizabeth !
[ III ]
Live ! Live ! Live !
Live !
Yes !
No ...
No !
It 's alive .
[ THUMPING ON METAL ]
[ III ]
[ GRUNTING ]
No .
What have I done ?
" Massive birth defects .
Greatly enhanced physical strength .
But resulting reanimant
is malfunctional and pitiful
and dead . "
Tomorrow this journal and its secrets must be destroyed
forever .
Oh , God .
[ CRYING ]
[ THUD ]
Aah !
[ GROANING ]
No !
You fool , Victor Frankenstein of Geneva .
How could you know what you 'd unleashed ?
How is it pieced together ? Bits of thieves , bits of murderers ...
Evil stitched to evil stitched to evil .
Do you really believe this thing will thank you for its monstrous birth ?
Evil will have its revenge .
God help your loved ones .
[ III ]
[ PEOPLE CHATTERING ]
What do you think you 're doing ?
Aah ! He 's got cholera ! He 's the one who 's been spreading the plague !
Get him !
[ PEOPLE YELLING AND WOMEN SCREAM ]
[ III ]
[ GRUNTING ]
MAN 1 : Come here , you- -
[ ROARS ]
WOMAN : Keep away from him .
MAN 2 : No , kill him now !
MAN 3 : He went this way .
HENRY : There now . Easy . Easy . Just a bit .
That 's it . There , now , rest easy . Henry , you 're here .
Of course I 'm here .
It was touch and go with you , though . Just a bit more .
I feared cholera , turned out to be pneumonia .
Yes , I 'm becoming something of a doctor .
Even Krempe seems pleased with me .
At this rate , I might even pass Anatomy .
The epidemic ? Dreadful .
There 's nothing we can do for them .
The vulnerable , anyone who 's without shelter or food ,
the newborns , especially , will die .
Are you sure ? I 'm certain of it .
Thank God .
What do you mean ?
Nothing .
Well then , that 's my shift finished .
I 'll see you later .
[ PIANO PLAYING ]
Elizabeth .
[ III ]
[ SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY ]
VICTOR : Please , please , forgive me ! Of course I do . Of course .
Victor , I don 't know what you 're working on , and I don 't want to know .
But it nearly killed you .
It 's over , it 's finished . It should never have started .
It 's dead ! It 's dead .
[ FLUTE PLAYING IN DISTANCE ]
[ LATCH RATTLES ]
WOMAN : Felix ! FELIX : Yes ?
WOMAN : Don 't forget the onion scraps .
FELIX : All right , I 've got them .
Go on , get .
Come on . Come on .
Go on , go on . Go on . Get .
How are the pigs ?
FELIX : They 're happy they 've been fed .
How are your hands ? FELIX : Oh , they 're bleeding again .
MARIE : Let me see them .
[ MARIE HUMMING AND FELIX GRUNTS ]
FELIX : That 's better .
MARIE : There .
The soup 's ready .
THOMAS : Come on , Grandpa . Sit down .
GRANDPA : Thank you .
[ III ]
[ THUDDING ]
We 'll never get through the winter with this yield .
The ground 's frozen hard . We 'll sell another pig at market .
We can 't . Not until they lift the quarantine .
Even then , it 's one less for us . Last month 's rent , he 'll be back for that .
Come on . We 'll do this together .
You 're right .
We 've got to , before the snow comes .
Come on , then .
The ground 's frozen solid . We haven 't the strength to do this .
We 'd need 20 men to work this field . It 's useless !
We should stop now . It 's getting late .
We don 't have enough to eat .
We 'll manage . Let 's go .
Look . Look .
[ LAUGHS ]
They must be gifts from the Good Spirit of the Forest .
Father , nothing in this life comes free of cost .
I would like to know who and why .
THOMAS : Was it , Grandpa ? Was it ? Was it the Good Spirit ?
GRANDPA : I believe it was .
FELIX : Will you stop filling their head with nonsense ?
[ TWIG SNAPS ]
Who 's there ?
Felix ? Children ?
MARIE : Right .
What 's this one ?
Fr- - Eh- - Nd .
Friend ? Ha , ha . Friend ! Well done !
That 's very good .
You 've got lots of friends , haven 't you ? Grandpa and ...
Friend ...
Friend .
Family .
Ff- - Fa ..
Father .
Now , this is very important . You must travel with them for the entire journey .
This equipment must not be left unattended .
My father will personally take delivery of them in Geneva . Do you understand ?
I do , sir . Thank you .
HEN RY : Going somewhere ? ELIZABETH : Henry , look .
Look at this locket Victor gave me . Isn 't it beautiful ?
Yes , it 's lovely . ls this really you ?
Yes , it 's a bad likeness , I know .
But for now , it will serve instead of a ring , huh ?
HENRY : Congratulations on the entirely expected !
When ? As soon as we get home .
Ha , ha . Oh .
I can 't believe we 'll be there for New Year 's Eve .
Victor 's going to take over Father 's practice .
And expand it .
I 'm going on ahead now the quarantine 's being lifted .
There 's so much to do for the wedding .
Now , the practice needs a partner . Now , there 's not much money ,
but there is food and board and some very good company .
And it 's the ideal position for someone who has finally passed Anatomy .
And so we were wondering if
there was anybody that you could recommend ?
Victor , I- - I don 't know what to say .
VICTOR : Well , please say yes .
Yes . ELIZABETH : Yes !
Yes , yes ! VICTOR : Yes !
And you can write that down in your journal !
[ LAUGHING AND SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ III ]
" This is ...
the journal ...
of ...
Victor ...
Frankenstein ...
of ...
Geneva . "
FELIX : Come on , quickly .
Come on , then , off you go . Quickly , now .
Merry Christmas . Merry Christmas .
Come on , now . Come on . Time for bed .
MARIE : In you go .
CREATURE : " For the Good Spirit of the Forest . "
Are you the Good Spirit of the Forest ?
Not exactly . Where 's your father ?
I said , where 's your father ?
Who 's there ? Maggie ?
No . Oh , it 's you .
What have you done to Maggie ? ls he in there ?
Hiding behind a blind old man ?
Get away ! Get away !
LANDLORD : Don 't blame me .
Blame your son for not paying his rent on time .
[ FLOOR CREAKS ]
[ LANDLORD SCREAMS ]
My God .
Thank you , my friend . Thank you so much .
Won 't you come and sit by the fire ?
Please , don 't be afraid .
Come . Come in .
Have a rest , sit down .
Ah . That 's better .
I 'm glad you finally came in .
A man shouldn 't have to hide in the shadows .
Better that way , for me .
Why ?
People are afraid .
Except you .
It can 't be as bad as that .
Worse .
I can " see " you with my hands , if you 'll trust me .
Papa , Papa , he hurl Grandpa ! FELIX : Who hurt Grandpa ?
MARIE : What was that noise ? FELIX : Tell me what the noise was .
What happened , Maggie ?
Poor man .
Have you no friends ?
There are some people .
But they don 't know me .
Why do you not go to them ?
Because I am so very ...
Ugly -
And they are so very ...
beautiful .
FELIX : Father ! Get out of here !
Get out of here , monster .
Leave him alone !
We have to leave here .
[ SOBBING ]
[ III ]
No .
[ GRUNTS ]
[ III ]
[ ROARS ]
I will have revenge !
Frankenstein !
[ III ]
Geneva .
Yay ! MAN : Quickly , quickly .
She 's here , she 's here ! ELIZABETH : Willie !
We got your letter ! We got your letter !
It 's the first one I was allowed to read .
Congratulations , Elizabeth .
I 'm happy for you . Thank you , Justine .
Oh , is that the locket ?
Oh . Look how handsome Victor is .
Elizabeth , can I take this to show Peter ?
Yes , but , Willie , it 's not a toy .
Let him go . Let him go . Don 't dawdle , William !
[ JUSTINE MRS. MORTIZ LAUGHING ]
Justine , you idiot . Pay attention .
Anyone would think you 're the one that 's getting married .
Yes , Mother . ELIZABETH : What 's wrong ?
JUSTINE : Nothing . Really .
MRS. MORITZ : Just leave it . You 've ruined it now .
[ FLUTE PLAYING ]
No ! No !
Frankenstein .
You , with me .
FATHER : Have you seen Willie ? Isn 't he back yet ?
Claude rode over to find out if he 'd lost track of time .
They say he never arrived . Far too late for him to still be out .
[ III ]
William ! MAN : William !
William ! William !
Willie !
[ THUNDER RUMBLING AND MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ CRYING ]
Willie ...
Willie !
This isn 't a game !
It 's so late .
We 're all so tired . I 'm so tired .
Father ! I 'm so pleased to see you .
What 's wrong ?
[ THUNDER CRASHES ]
[ III ]
[ WHIMPERING ]
[ DOG BARKING IN DISTANCE ]
MAN : William !
VICTOR : We checked the east ridge . There 's nothing there .
Damn !
Elizabeth ?
I found him !
Elizabeth !
No !
[ SOBBING ]
We did everything we could , sir .
You just rest easy now . We did everything we could .
MRS. MORITZ : Sir , I 'm terrified for my girl . She 's still out looking for William .
We parted badly . I was cruel to her . I didn 't mean it .
I think she finds it very hard now , with your wedding . She loves you dearly .
I couldn 't bear it if anything happened to her .
She 's all I 've got . Please , help me !
We 'll organize another search now that ifs light .
We will find her , Mrs. Moritz , I promise .
[ SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY ]
How is Father ? His heart is breaking .
[ KNOCKING ON DOOR ]
Mr. Frankenstein ,
we 've apprehended the murderer , not five miles from here hiding in a barn .
We found this on her . It 's yours , I believe , sir ?
Sir , you must come immediately .
The townspeople have gone mad .
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
My God . What are they doing ?
They must have broken into the jail !
Well , for God 's sake , man , can 't you stop them ?
They 've gone wild ! This is a lynching mob !
Stop ! This is unlawful .
Justine . Justine !
[ SCREAMING ]
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
Victor ! Help me ! I was trying to find him !
I went to the lake , but it was dark !
I wanted to bring him to you !
He must be there for the wedding ! I 'm sorry ! He 's so tiny .
[ III ]
[ SCREAMING ]
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
VICTOR : We managed to close the gates on the mob , Claude .
What about Justine ?
We 've cut her down . We can bury her in the morning .
Thank you , Claude . Get to bed .
CREATURE : The sea of ice .
I will meet you there
on the sea of ice .
Oh , Justine , forgive me .
Victor , tell me . Who is this man ?
How do you know he 's responsible ?
I 'll tell you everything after I 've destroyed him .
But if what you say is true , then surely this is a matter
for the police . They wouldn 't understand .
Well , neither do I.
Then just accept it .
[ GRUNTING AND PANTING ]
[ III ]
[ GRUNTING ]
CREATURE : Get up .
Get up .
You do speak .
Yes , I speak .
And read .
And think .
And know the ways of man .
How did you find me ?
Your journal .
Then you mean to kill me .
No .
You murdered my brother , didn 't you ?
I took him by the throat with one hand ,
lifted him off the ground
and slowly crushed his neck .
And as I killed him , I saw your face .
You gave me these emotions . But you didn 't tell me how to use them .
Now two people are dead
because of us .
Why ?
There 's something at work in my soul which I do not understand .
What of my soul ? Do I have one ?
Or was that a part you left out ?
Who were these people of which I am comprised ?
Good people ? Bad people ?
Materials , nothing more . You 're wrong .
Do you know I knew how to play this ?
In which part of me did this knowledge reside ?
In these hands ?
In this mind ? In this heart ?
And reading and speaking .
Not things learned so much as things remembered .
Trace memories in the brain , perhaps .
Did you ever consider the consequences of your actions ?
You gave me life , and then you left me to die .
Who am I ?
You ...
I don 't know .
And you think I 'm evil .
What can I do ?
There is something I want . A friend .
A friend ?
Companion .
A female .
Someone like me .
So she won 't hate me .
Like you ?
Oh , God , you don 't know what you 're asking .
I do know that
for the sympathy of one living being ,
I would make peace with all .
I have love in me the likes of which
you can scarcely imagine .
And rage , the likes of which you would not believe .
If I cannot satisfy the one
I will indulge the other .
And if I consent , how will you live ?
We would travel north , my bride and I ,
to the furthest reaches of the Pole .
Where no man has ever set foot .
There , we would live out our lives
together .
No human eye would ever see us again .
This , I vow .
You must help me . Please .
If it is possible to right this wrong ,
then I will do it .
Victor ! Victor .
Are you all right ?
Yes , I 'm safe . I 'm safe . What happened ?
Tell us .
Victor .
Victor , you have to tell us what happened !
One month , that 's all I ask .
And then we can be married ,
and we can forget this whole business .
I promise . Promise ? Promise .
Oh , don 't dare use that word to me .
You promised to tell me who this man was .
You promised to abandon this work for good .
Your promises don 't mean anything . Elizabeth .
I have to leave this house . What are you saying ?
Where will you go ? I don 't know .
Somewhere I can recover . Well , look . This is ridiculous .
I haven 't got time to argue .
Oh , isn 't it convenient ? Or doesn 't it fit in with your plans ?
Don 't you ever think of anyone or anything but yourself ?
God forgive me .
[ III ]
Why her ?
Materials , remember ? Nothing more .
Your words . No .
You will honor your promise to me !
I will not .
Go on , kill me now .
That is mild compared to what will come .
If you deny me my wedding night , I will be with you on yours .
Elizabeth !
Elizabeth .
Wait . Wait , please wait . Please .
I have to speak to you . Please !
What do you want to say ?
Don 't go .
[ III ]
Please , don 't go .
I 'm frightened .
Of what ?
I have done something so terrible ,
so evil .
And I 'm frightened that if I tell you the truth
that I will lose you .
You 'll lose me if you don 't .
I .. -
don 't know ...
what ...
to do .
[ CRYING ]
Will you marry me , Victor ?
Marry me today .
Tomorrow , tell me everything .
But you must tell me the truth .
And together , we can face anything .
Whatever you 've done , whatever has happened ,
I love you .
To share the truth , the whole truth , for good or ill ,
to stand by each other in sickness and in health ,
and in joy , from this day forward
till death do you part .
Who is this man , sir ?
How shall we know him ? Believe me , you 'll know him .
He killed Master William , and Justine Moritz died for it .
No hesitation , lads . Shoot the bastard on sight !
Henry ?
HEN RY : Don 't worry about a thing .
You two look after each other . I 'll look after your father .
[ III ]
I 'm sorry , sir . The last ferry 's gone .
There 's nothing now till morning . Damn .
I 'll ride on ahead and secure you lodgings for the night .
Thank you , Claude . Come on .
Keep your pistols dry ! MAN : They 're dry enough .
And if they fail , we 've others . And if those fail ,
we can always gut the bastard .
Go to your post . Yes , sir .
Don 't worry , sir . You 're well guarded .
Now , why don 't you go on upstairs to your wife ?
It 's not often a man has his wedding night .
[ III ]
You 're soaking .
Brother and sister no more .
Now husband and wife .
[ FLUTE PLAYING ]
Victor ?
Lock the door .
Lock the door . Victor .
I saw him in a flash of lightning . He ran to the lake .
You two stay here .
[ THUNDER CRASHES ]
MAN : We lost him .
VICTOR : Elizabeth !
Don 't bother to scream .
Please ... Please don 't hurt me .
You are lovelier than I ever could have imagined .
VICTOR : Elizabeth !
Elizabeth !
[ III ]
I keep my promises !
[ GUNSHOTS ]
[ VICTOR SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ SOBBING ]
For God 's sake , tell me what happened .
No point . I know what I have to do .
God . No , Victor ! You can 't do this , I won 't let you !
She 's gone . I love her . What would you do ?
Leave her in peace . Peace ? You call this peace ?
Think my father wouldn 't have done this for my mother ?
Your father 's dead .
Then there 's nothing left to lose .
Nothing but your soul .
[ III ]
Live !
No !
Live . Live .
Yes . Yes . Yes .
[ COUGHING ]
Say my name .
Please , say my name .
Remember ! You must remember .
Elizabeth ?
That 's it .
That 's it , you remember .
Now , stand . Stand .
[ GRUNTING ]
Yes . Yes . Yes .
You remember .
[ III ]
[ THUNDER CRASHES ]
She 's beautiful .
She 's not for you .
Come .
Elizabeth ?
Say my name .
Elizabeth .
Yes .
Elizabeth !
You 're beautiful .
Say my name .
Elizabeth , come to me .
Come to me .
[ III ]
Say my name , Elizabeth .
Vic ...
That 's right , Elizabeth .
Victor .
No , you 're mine .
You 're mine .
Leave her alone ! No ! Get away from her . She 's mine .
VICTOR : She 's mine ! She said my name ! She remembers !
She 's mine !
[ SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ III ]
VICTOR : No !
[ GASPS ]
VICTOR : All that I once loved lies in a shallow grave
by my hand .
I followed the trail he left for me- -
North .
Always north .
- -For months now
with one intent :
To kill him .
Now ...
I 'm tired .
I 'm so very , very tired .
What did he say ?
He 's dead .
He died raving about some phantom .
What is it out there , captain ?
He told me a story that ...
couldn 't be true .
He was mad , I think .
A warming breeze .
The ice will melt yet .
And what then , captain ?
We head north . No .
[ CREATURE GROANS ]
[ CRYING ]
[ III ]
Who are you ?
He never gave me a name .
Why do you weep ?
He was my father .
WALTON : " And yea , I gave my heart to know wisdom
and to know madness and folly ,
and I perceived that all is vanity and vexation of spirit .
For in much wisdom is much grief ,
and he that increaseth knowledge , increaseth sorrow .
For God shall bring every work
and every secret thing into judgment ,
whether it be good , or whether it be evil . "
Captain- - He has a right to bear witness .
[ ICE CREAKING ]
[ III ]
Jesus , ifs breaking up !
[ MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY ]
[ GRUNTS ]
Get back to the ship , captain .
Leave the damn torch ! Leave it !
Come with us .
I am done with man .
MAN : Hang on , I 've got you !
Help ! Help !
MAN : Here , captain . Here , captain . Quick , grab my hand !
Where to now , captain ?
Home .
[ III ]